Good afternoon everyone welcome to 213 it's good to see you
大家下午好，欢迎来到213，很高兴见到你
Just a reminder that your attack lab is due tonight at 11:59 p.m.
请提醒你，你的攻击实验室将于今晚11点59分到期。
You have one grace day for this lab
这个实验室你有一个宽限期
And cache lab we'll go out it right about the same time
和缓存实验室我们将在同一时间出去
Now it's going to be a little tight for cache labs it'll be due next Thursday
现在它对缓存实验室来说有点紧张，它将在下周四到期
So you might want to you might want to get started on that soon
所以你可能希望你很快就能开始这么做
Last lecture we learned about the memory hierarchy and the idea of caching
最后一节课我们了解了内存层次结构和缓存的概念
Today we're going to look at a very important kind of cache
今天我们将看一个非常重要的缓存
Which are called cache memories
哪些被称为缓存
And they're very important to you as a programmer
作为程序员，它们对你非常重要
Because they can have such a big impact on the performance of your program
因为它们会对程序的性能产生如此大的影响
So if you know about these the existence of these cache memories and you know how they work
因此，如果你知道这些缓存的存在，你知道它们是如何工作的
As a programmer you'll be able to take advantage of that in your programs
作为程序员，你将能够在程序中利用它
So last time we looked at the memory hierarchy is a collection of storage devices
所以上次我们查看内存层次结构是一个存储设备的集合
With smaller,costlier and faster devices at the top and slower cheaper and much larger devices at the at the bottom
顶部设备更小，更昂贵，速度更快，底部设备更便宜，设备更大
And then at each level in this hierarchy
然后在这个层次结构的每个级别
The device at level k serves as a cache holds a subset of the blocks of
级别k的设备用作高速缓存保存块的子集
That are contained in the device at the lower level at level k+1
它包含在较低级别的设备中，级别为k + 1
Now recall the general idea of caching so we have a memory
现在回想一下缓存的一般概念，这样我们就有了记忆
It's an array of bytes and we break it up arbitrarily into a collection of blocks
它是一个字节数组，我们将它任意分解为一个块集合
And these this memory is larger slower and cheaper
而这些内存更慢更便宜
And so it's,and it's much larger than than a cache which is smaller faster and more expensive
它就是这样，而且它比一个更小，更快，更昂贵的缓存大得多
And which holds a subset of the blocks that are contained in the main memory
并且它包含主存储器中包含的块的子集
And then blocks are copied back and forth between the cache in the memory in these block size transfer units
然后，在这些块大小传输单元中，块在存储器中的高速缓存之间来回复制
So for example if our program requests a word that's in contained in block number 4
因此，例如，如果我们的程序请求包含在块编号4中的单词
It asks the cache to return the word that's contained in block 4
它要求缓存返回块4中包含的单词
The cache looks and it's at the blocks that it's the subset of the blocks
缓存看起来就是块，它是块的子集
That it's stored discovers that block 4 is not there
存储它发现块4不存在
So it asks the main memory to send it block 4
所以它要求主存储器发送它块4
Which it does and when that block arrives at the cache
它的作用以及该块何时到达缓存
The cache stores it but potentially overwriting some existing block
缓存存储它但可能覆盖一些现有块
Similarly if our program asks for a data word
同样，如果我们的程序要求数据字
If that's contained within block 10
如果包含在第10块中
The cache looks sees that it doesn't have that block
缓存外观看到它没有该块
So it requests that block for memory which copies it into the cache
因此它请求将内存块复制到缓存中
Which overwrites an existing block
这会覆盖现有的块
Now subsequently if our program asks for a request
现在，如果我们的程序要求请求
If our program references a word that's contained in block 10
如果我们的程序引用了块10中包含的单词
For example then the cache then we have a hit and the cache can return that block immediately
例如，然后缓存然后我们有一个命中，缓存可以立即返回该块
Without going through the expensive operation of contacting memory and fetching that block from memory
无需经历昂贵的联系内存操作并从内存中获取该块
Now there's a very important class of caches these so called cache memories
现在有一类非常重要的缓存，即所谓的缓存
Which are contained in the CPU chip itself
哪些包含在CPU芯片本身中
And are managed completely by hardware
并且完全由硬件管理
And they're implemented using fast SRAM memories
它们是使用快速SRAM存储器实现的
And the idea for this cache which write next to the register file
以及写入寄存器文件旁边的缓存的想法
Is to hold frequently access blocks or blocks from main memory that are accessed frequently
是经常访问主存储器中经常访问的块或块
Okay so hopefully because of the principle of locality
好吧，希望因为地方原则
Most of our requests for data will actually be served out of this cache memory and a few cycles
我们对数据的大多数请求实际上都会从这个缓存内存中提供几个周期
Rather than from this slow main memory
而不是从这个缓慢的主存
Now cache memories are managed completely in hardware
现在，高速缓存存储器完全由硬件管理
So this means that the heart there's ,here has to be hardware logic that knows
所以这意味着那里的心脏，这里必须是知道的硬件逻辑
How to look for blocks in the cache and determine whether or not a particular block is contained there
如何查找缓存中的块并确定是否包含特定块
So cache memories are have to be organized in a very kind of strict simple way
因此，必须以非常严格的简单方式组织高速缓存存储器
So that the logic the lookup logic can be pretty simple
因此查找逻辑的逻辑可以非常简单
So this is very all cache memories are organized in the following way
因此，所有缓存存储器都按以下方式组织
You can think of the cache as an array of S=2^s sets
你可以将缓存视为S = 2 ^ s集的数组
Ok each set consists of E=2^e lines
好的每一组都包含E = 2 ^ e行
Where each line consists of a block of B=2^b bytes of data
其中每一行由一个B = 2 ^ b字节的数据块组成
A valid bit which indicates whether these data bits are actually that the bits and the data block are actually meaningful right
一个有效位，指示这些数据位是否实际上是位和数据块实际上是有意义的
It's possible they could just be random bits like you know when you first turn on the machine
当你第一次打开机器时，它们可能只是你知道的随机位
There's nothing in the cache
缓存中没有任何内容
But those bits will have values right that they'll lead to be ones or zeros
但这些位将具有正确的值，它们将导致为1或0
But they won't actually correspond to data
但它们实际上并不符合数据
Okay so the valid bit tells us if these B bytes actually mean anything
好的，有效位告诉我们这些B字节是否实际意味着什么
And then there's some additional bits called the tag bits
然后还有一些称为标记位的附加位
Which will help us search for blocks which I'll show you in a minute
这将帮助我们搜索我将在一分钟内向你展示的块
Now when we talk about our cache size
现在我们谈谈我们的缓存大小
We're referring to the number of data bytes that are contained in blocks
我们指的是块中包含的数据字节数
And so each cache has there's S sets
所以每个缓存都有S套
There's E blocks per set
每套都有E块
And there's B bytes per block
并且每个块有B个字节
Ok so the total cache size C=S*E*B
好的总缓存大小C = S * E * B.
Ok now so there's a lot of terms to sort of keep straight and it's very easy to get
好了，所以有很多条款可以保持直线，而且很容易获得
To confuse the difference between lines and blocks and lines and sets
混淆行和块以及行和集之间的差异
Okay so we'll go through some examples and hopefully these will see these will start to make more sense
好的，我们将通过一些例子，希望这些将会开始变得更有意义
Now let's look at in general how the cache hardware implements a read
现在让我们来看一下缓存硬件如何实现读取
So when our program accesses, when our program executes an instruction
因此，当我们的程序访问时，我们的程序执行指令
That references some word in memory
这引用了记忆中的一些词
The CPU sends that address to the cache
CPU将该地址发送到缓存
And asks and it asks the cache to return the word the word at that address
并询问并要求缓存在该地址返回单词
So the cache takes that address
因此缓存占用该地址
This would be a 64-bit address in case of x86-64
对于x86-64，这将是64位地址
And it divides the address into a number of regions
它将地址划分为多个区域
Which are determined by the organization of the cache
这由缓存的组织决定
Okay they're determined by those parameters S sets
好的，他们是由那些参数决定的
The s the number of sets a the number of lines per set and b the size of each data block
s设置的数量是每组的行数，b是每个数据块的大小
So the low order bits there are b low order bits which determine the offset in the block
因此，低阶位有b个低阶位，用于确定块中的偏移量
That that word starts at
那个词开始于
Okay the next s bits are treated as an unsigned integer
好的，接下来的s位被视为无符号整数
Which serves as an index into the array of sets
它作为集合数组的索引
Okay remember we just think of these as think of this cache as an array of set
好的记住，我们只是将这些想法视为一个集合数组
The set index bits provide the index into this array of sets
设置的索引位为这个数组提供索引
And then all of the remaining bits
然后是所有剩下的比特
All of the remaining t bits constitute what we call tag
所有剩余的t位构成了我们称之为标签的东西
Which will help us when we do our search
这将有助于我们进行搜索
So the cache logic takes this address
因此缓存逻辑采用此地址
And it first extracts the the set index
它首先提取集合索引
And uses that to,as an index into this array to identify the set that
并使用它作为此数组的索引来识别该集合
If this block is in the set,I'm sorry,if the data word
如果这个块在集合中，我很抱歉，如果是数据字
If the block that contains the data word at this address is in the cache
如果包含此地址的数据字的块在缓存中
It's going to be in the set denoted by the the set index
它将在set索引表示的集合中
So first it identifies which index to look in
首先，它确定要查看的索引
And then it checks the tag,it checks all of the lines in that set
然后它检查标签，它检查该组中的所有行
To see if there's any of those lines have a matching tag
要查看这些行中是否有任何匹配的标记
That a tag that matches the the t the tag bits and the address
这是一个与标签位和地址匹配的标签
And it checks to see if the valid bit is turned on
并检查有效位是否打开
So if those two conditions holds if there's a line anywhere in the set
因此，如果这两个条件成立，那么集合中的任何地方都有一条线
As of where the valid bit is one and there's a matching tag
至于有效位是1并且有匹配标记的位置
Then we have a hit okay then the block that we're looking for is contained in this set
然后我们点击好了，然后我们正在寻找的块包含在这个集合中
Okay if we...once we determine that with that we've identified the block
好的，如果我们......一旦我们确定了那个，我们已经确定了该块
Then the cache uses that the low-order b bits to determine where that
然后缓存使用低位b位来确定它的位置
Where the data we're interested in begins okay within that block
我们感兴趣的数据在该块内开始正常
All right let's look at a more specific example for a the simplest kind of cache
好吧，让我们看一个最简单的缓存的更具体的例子
Which is when E=1 when there's only one line per set
当每组只有一行时E = 1
Okay so E=1 one line per set
好的，所以E = 1每行一行
This kind of cache is called a direct mapped cache
这种缓存称为直接映射缓存
So here we have S sets each set consists of a single line
所以这里我们有S组，每组由一条线组成
And now suppose our program references the data item
现在假设我们的程序引用了数据项
And a particular address the CPU sense that address to the cache
并且CPU感知到缓存的地址的特定地址
The cache takes that address breaks it up into these into these three fields
缓存将该地址分解为这三个字段
For this particular address the block offset is four
对于此特定地址，块偏移量为四
And the set index is one and then there's some tag bits which we'll just denote with is a color pink
设置索引是一个，然后有一些标记位，我们只是用粉红色表示
So the cache extracts the set index which is one
因此缓存提取的集合索引为1
And then it uses that as the index into the set
然后它使用它作为集合的索引
And then it just ignores all the other the sets
然后它只是忽略了所有其他的集合
If the block we're looking for is...is in the cache it's going to be in this inset number one
如果我们正在寻找的块是...在缓存中它将在这个插入的第一个
Then it does the comparison of the tag bits and the valid bits
然后它进行标记位和有效位的比较
And assume that they assume that valid bits on and that it matches
并假设他们假设有效位和它匹配
Then it looks at the block offset which is four
然后它查看块偏移量为4
And which tells it that the four bit in suppose that that's what the instruction was referencing
并且它告诉它四位假设这就是指令引用的内容
The four byte in begins that offset for
四个字节开始偏移为
So now the cache takes this int and it sends it back to the to the CPU which puts it in the register
所以现在缓存采用这个int并将它发送回CPU，并将其放入寄存器中
Okay if the tag doesn't match then the old-line, if the tag doesn't match then there's a miss
好的，如果标签与旧线不匹配，如果标签不匹配，则表示未命中
And in that case the cache has to fetch the block the corresponding block from memory
在这种情况下，缓存必须从内存中获取相应块的块
And then overwrite this block in the line
然后在行中覆盖此块
And then it can serve,then it can fetch,it can get the word out of the block and send it back to the processor
然后它可以服务，然后它可以获取，它可以从块中取出字并将其发送回处理器
Okay now let me ask you a question just to see you kind of check to see you're following along with this
好的，现在让我问你一个问题，只是为了看看你有什么检查看到你跟着这个
So if there's a miss
所以，如果有一个错过
And the cache has two requests the block for memory
并且缓存有两个请求内存块
Fetch it from memory and then overwrite the the block in the current line
从内存中获取它，然后覆盖当前行中的块
Does it also have to change the tag bits or do those stay the same?
是否还必须更改标记位或保持不变？
So does the do the tag bits that were in this line get overwritten with a different value
那么这一行中的标记位是否会被不同的值覆盖
Or is it the same? same? different? same? different?
还是一样吗？相同？不同？相同？不同？
Now why would it be different ?
现在为什么会有所不同？
-we haven't changed yes-[student speaking]-I'm sorry oh-[student speaking]
- 我们没有改变是 -  [学生说话]  - 对不起哦 -  [学生说话]
Oh it almost certainly has different data
哦，它几乎肯定有不同的数据
But just have a different address
但只是有一个不同的地址
Exactly it missed because the tag
完全错过了因为标签
It missed because the tag didn't match
它错过了因为标签不匹配
If the valid bit was false and the tag match then that would also be a miss
如果有效位为假且标记匹配，那么这也将是未命中
Oh then you wouldn't...okay that's right,that's...okay good good good,okay,great
哦，那你就不会......好吧，那是......好吧好的好，好的，好的
All right let me do a little, let me do a really simple specific example of a how direct map cache works
好吧，让我做一点，让我做一个关于直接地图缓存如何工作的一个非常简单的具体例子
I want you to understand in real detail how this would work
我希望你真正了解这是如何工作的
But I also want to make a point for about the weakness of direct mapped cache is and why
但我也想说明直接映射缓存的弱点和原因
Why you would want to have more than one line per set
为什么你希望每组有多行
Okay this is a really simple we have our memory system consists of 16 bytes
好的，这是一个非常简单的我们的内存系统由16个字节组成
Ok so it's not a very useful system with 4 bit addresses
好的，这不是一个非常有用的4位地址系统
And it's broken up into blocks of 2 bytes each
它被分解为每个2字节的块
Our cache consists of 4 sets with one block per set
我们的缓存由4组组成，每组一个区块
Now 4 bytes,4 bit addresses
现在4个字节，4位地址
Because B=2, that's 2^1 we only need 1 block offset bit
因为B = 2，即2 ^ 1，我们只需要1个块偏移位
Right there's only 2 bytes in a block so the byte we're looking for is either at 0 or 1
在一个块中只有2个字节，所以我们要查找的字节是0或1
Okay because we have 4 sets we need set index bits
好的，因为我们有4套，我们需要设置索引位
And then the remaining bits are always tag bits in this case there's just one tag bit
然后剩余的位总是标记位，在这种情况下只有一个标记位
All right now let's suppose that our program executes instructions
好了，我们假设我们的程序执行指令
That reference the following memory address is 0,1,7,8 and 0
该引用以下内存地址为0,1,7,8和0
And these references are reads that they're reading one byte per read
这些引用是读取它们每次读取一个字节的读取
Okay like I said this is a really simple system
好吧我说这是一个非常简单的系统
So let's look at what happens now
那么让我们来看看现在发生了什么
We start tag,initially,cache is empty valid bits are all set to zero
我们开始标记，最初，缓存是空的有效位都被设置为零
And now the cache receives the request for the byte that's at address 0
现在，缓存接收对地址为0的字节的请求
So it extracts the set index bits which in this case are 00
因此它提取设置索引位，在本例中为00
So these so it's going to look in set 0
所以这些它将在第0组中查找
For and in this case since valid is 0 it's just a miss ok
对于和在这种情况下，因为有效是0，它只是一个错过确定
So it fetches that block from memory sticks the block
因此它从存储器中取出块来阻止块
So this memory this is the...this is using array notation for memory
所以这个内存就是......这是使用数组符号表示内存
So this is like the the bytes that extend from offset 0 to offset 1 inclusive in memory
所以这就像在内存中从偏移0延伸到偏移1的字节
The tag bit is 0 and the valid bit is 1
标记位为0，有效位为1
Ok now the next address that comes by is for address 1
好的，现在下一个地址是地址1
Well that's a hit right...because we...that block the block that contains the byte at address 1 is already in the cache
好吧，这是一个正确的...因为我们...阻止包含地址1字节的块已经在缓存中
The tag and the tags match okay so we're good that's a hit
标签和标签匹配正常，所以我们很好，这是一个打击
You now we get address 7
你现在我们得到地址7
So the cache extracts the set index bits,which in this case are 11 or 4 or 3 rather
因此缓存提取设置的索引位，在这种情况下是11或4或3
Looks in set 3 there's no valid bit,so that's a miss and it loads the the data from memory
在第3组中查找没有有效位，因此这是一个未命中并且它从内存加载数据
That spans bytes 6~7
跨越字节6~7
In this case the the tag bit is 0
在这种情况下，标记位为0
Okay so we record that in our metadata
好的，我们在元数据中记录了这一点
Okay the next reference that comes by is 8
好的，下一个参考是8
Now 8 has a set index of 0,00
现在8的集合索引为0,00
But that's currently occupied by block zero one
但那个目前被零块一个占据
And we can tell that because address eight has a tag of one
我们可以告诉你，因为地址8有一个标签
And the existing block,the block at the earlier address at address zero has a tag of zero so that's a miss so
而现有的块，地址为零的早期地址处的块具有零标记，因此这是一个未命中
So now we have to go fetch the block containing byte number eight into memory
所以现在我们必须将包含字节数8的块提取到内存中
So now we have bytes 8-9 and we in our new tag bit
所以现在我们有8-9字节，我们在新的标签位
Okay now the next instruction is for byte 0
好的，现在下一条指令是字节0
And we just replaced,we had that it,we had that in our cache and we just replaced it
我们刚刚更换了，我们就拥有了它，我们在缓存中有了它，我们只是替换它
So it's another miss so that's unfortunate
所以这是另一个错过，所以这是不幸的
And it's the only reason we missed it is because we've got just one line per set
这是我们错过它的唯一原因是因为我们每组只有一行
Right so we were forced to overwrite
是的，所以我们被迫覆盖
That that block containing bytes,the block zero one when we missed on block eight nine
那块包含字节的块，当我们在块8九时错过时块0
Okay and you see there's plenty of room in our cache we've still got,we've got two lines
好的，你看我们的缓存中有足够的空间我们还有，我们有两条线
That we haven't even access right so we've our cache is plenty big
我们甚至都没有访问权限，因此我们的缓存非常大
But just because of the low associativity of our cache
但仅仅因为我们的缓存关联性低
And the the sort of the pattern the access pattern that we were presented with
以及我们呈现的访问模式的模式类型
We've got a miss that really was kind of unnecessary
我们有一个真的有点不必要的小姐
So oh yeah sorry
哦，对不起
[student speaking]
[学生说话]
Six,so when we referenced a seven
六，所以当我们引用七
It's actually the it's at offset one in that block 6-7
它实际上就是6-7区块中的偏移量
Okay since blocks are two bytes they'll always start on an even multiple
好吧，因为块是两个字节，它们总是以偶数倍开始
Any other questions
还有其他问题吗
Okay so this sort of is the reason why you have caches have higher associativity,higher values of E
好的，所以这就是为什么你有缓存具有更高的关联性，更高的E值的原因
So let's look at...and so for values of E greater...for values of E greater than greater than 1
因此，让我们看看......对于E值大于......对于E的值大于1
We refer to them as E way set associative caches
我们将它们称为E路集关联缓存
So here E=2 so it's a 2-way it's 2-way associative
所以这里E = 2所以它是双向的，它是双向关联的
Let's suppose we have a 2-way associative cache
假设我们有一个双向关联缓存
So here we have an array of sets and now each set contains two lines ok instead of one line
所以这里我们有一组数组，现在每组包含两行ok而不是一行
And suppose we're presented with an address with the following form
并且假设我们被提供了具有以下形式的地址
We're looking for the word that begins at an off set of four inside our block
我们正在寻找从我们的区块内的一组四个开始的单词
At within set number one
在第一组内
Okay so the cache expects tracts that set index
好的，所以缓存需要设置索引的tracts
So this is set 0,this is set 1,this is set 2,throws away all the other sets
所以这设置为0，设置为1，设置为2，抛弃所有其他集
And now in parallel it searches,it searches the tags,it searches for a matching tag in both of these lines
现在并行搜索，搜索标签，搜索这两行中的匹配标签
And a valid bit so if we get a matching tag and a valid bit true
如果我们得到匹配的标签和有效位，则为有效位
Then we've got a hit
然后我们受到了打击
Now that yes yes
现在是的，是的
[student speaking]
[学生说话]
Oh it's a very good question,so there's hardware logic that does that compare
哦，这是一个非常好的问题，所以有比较的硬件逻辑
And that's the reason that as the number of...as the associativity goes up that logic gets more and more expensive
这就是因为随着关联性的增加，逻辑变得越来越昂贵
Okay it's like something...like you're kind of doing some kind of tree search
好吧，这就像是某种东西......就像你在做某种树搜索一样
And so that actually is the limit that's why..
所以这实际上是限制，这就是为什么..
I mean because in general right that if you take this to the limit there's just one set
我的意思是因为一般来说，如果你把它限制在极限，那么只有一套
With there's just...we call that a fully associative cache so there's just one set
只有...我们称之为完全关联的缓存，因此只有一组
And now any block...a block can go anywhere
而现在任何一块......一个块可以去任何地方
Right there's no constraints now where you place a block
现在没有限制，你放置一个块
But because of the complexity of that fully associative search
但由于完全关联搜索的复杂性
Those are very rare in fact we do see we'll see fully associative caches but their software caches
这些是非常罕见的，事实上我们确实看到我们会看到完全关联的缓存，但他们的软件缓存
Okay so in software,so the complexity the hardware
好的，在软件中，硬件的复杂性
And sort of doesn't
而有点不
Doesn't it's not worth the complexity of the hardware for the penalty of having a lower associativity
对于具有较低关联性的惩罚，不值得硬件的复杂性
Okay but there are some systems later on when we study virtual memory
好的，但是稍后我们研究虚拟内存时会有一些系统
In a virtual memory system the DRAM serves as a cache for data stored on the disk
在虚拟存储器系统中，DRAM用作存储在磁盘上的数据的高速缓存
And as we saw last time the penalty for a miss
正如我们上次看到一个小姐的点球
If you have a cache on DRAM and you miss and you have to go to disk
如果你在DRAM上有一个缓存但你错过了，你必须转到磁盘
The penalty is huge for that
And so because of that it's worth while having very complex search algorithms
因此，拥有非常复杂的搜索算法是值得的
In particular in a virtual memory system that the DRAM is implements a fully associative cache where blocks from disk can go anywhere
特别是在虚拟存储器系统中，DRAM实现了完全关联的高速缓存，其中来自磁盘的块可以到达任何地方
We'll get into that later when we look in virtual memory
But you're right you'll see in real systems
但你是对的，你会在真实的系统中看到
Nowadays that the number goes up right because feature sizes are going down and
Designers can afford to implement more expensive hardware
设计人员可以负担得起更昂贵的硬件
But the largest associativity are Intel systems that I know of is 16-way associative L3 caches
但最大的关联性是我所知道的英特尔系统是16路关联L3缓存
And then the others are 8-ways associative
然后其他人是8方式联想
So that's sort of the order of magnitude that's state of the art right now
所以这就是现在最先进的数量级
Okay so then once we've identified a match we use the set offset bits
好的，一旦我们确定匹配，我们就使用设置的偏移位
In this case we're accessing a short int, so four is the offset within the block of this
在这种情况下，我们正在访问一个短整数，因此四是该区块内的偏移量
The two byte short int which then we can return to the processor
两个字节短的int然后我们可以返回到处理器
Alright so let's do that same simulation that we did before
好吧，让我们做同样的模拟，我们之前做过
But this time with a 2-way associative cache
但这次使用了双向关联缓存
Now memory system is the same
现在记忆系统是一样的
But now instead of one set we have two sets
但现在我们有两套，而不是一套
And I mean I'm sorry instead of four sets we have two sets
我的意思是我很抱歉而不是四套我们有两套
So the cache,this is the same sized cache
所以缓存，这是相同大小的缓存
But we're just going to organize it differently, instead of 1-way instead of a direct mapped cache
但我们只是以不同的方式组织它，而不是单向而不是直接映射缓存
With four lines containing four lines,one line per set
四行包含四行，每行一行
We're going to implement a 2-way associative cache where we have two sets with two lines per set
我们将实现一个双向关联缓存，其中我们有两组，每组有两行
Okay so each case there's four total lines
好的，所以每个案例总共有四行
Question
题
[student speaking]
Oh so that that comes in with the request somehow
哦，以便以某种方式提出请求
And I actually don't know the details of that
而我实际上并不知道具体细节
It may...I guess there...it could ask for just...
它可能......我猜...它可以要求......
there could just be a default sighs maybe it's always a 64-byte word and then the processor extracts that the current bits
I actually don't know the details of that
我实际上不知道那个细节
But it either comes in on the request or there's a standard size that the processor then parses out
但它要么在请求中，要么处理器然后解析标准大小
We'll just assume that the cache knows the what size to return yes
我们假设缓存知道返回的大小是什么
[student speaking]
[学生说话]
How do you decide which block to replace?that's a really good question
你如何决定要替换哪个块？这是一个非常好的问题
So there's a lot of different algorithms
所以有很多不同的算法
The most common algorithm or a common algorithm is least recently used
最常用的算法或常用算法是最近最少使用的
So by locality you want to keep blocks in the cache that are being used a lot
因此，根据位置，你希望将缓存中的块保留在正在使用的块中
And so if a block isn't referenced for a long time by the principle of locality by sort of the inverse locality principle
因此，如果通过反向局部性原理的类型，通过局部性原理长时间不引用块
It's likely not to be addressed referenced in the near future
它可能不会在不久的将来被引用
So that's one algorithm
这就是一种算法
That you just keep track of and I'm not showing there needs to be additional bits
你只是跟踪，我没有显示那里需要额外的位
In the line to sort of keep like sort of virtual timestamps that
在排序中保持类似虚拟时间戳的那种
But that's sort of the general way you do it
但这是你做这件事的一般方式
Just try to keep the things that are the blocks being accessed the most frequently,most recently yes
只是尽量保持最常访问的块，最近是的
[student speaking]
[学生说话]
Okay the question is what determines the block size
好的问题是什么决定了块的大小
That's determined by the design of the memory system
这是由内存系统的设计决定的
So that's a fixed parameter of the memory system
所以这是内存系统的固定参数
So when the intel designers decided to put cache memories on their processors
因此，当英特尔设计师决定将缓存存储器放在他们的处理器上时
They decided that the block size would be 64 bytes
他们认为块大小为64字节
Sorry
抱歉
So the block size comes the block size comes first
因此块大小首先出现块大小
Then you determine how big you want your cache to be
然后确定你希望缓存的大小
Okay and you determine the associativity
好的，你确定了关联性
And then once you've determined the associativity and you know how big your cache is
然后，一旦确定了关联性，就知道缓存有多大
Then that determines the number of sets
然后确定集的数量
Okay so basically all of those the
好吧基本上所有这些
The the number of lines and the cat and the capacity
行数和猫的数量和容量
The number of lines per set is sort of a fixed high-level parameter design parameter
每组的行数是固定的高级参数设计参数
The size of the cache is a high-level design parameter
缓存的大小是高级设计参数
And then the number of sets then is induced from that
然后由此引发集合的数量
Okay yes
好的，是的
[student speaking]
[学生说话]
Ah that's yeah how does...so that's the replacement policy
啊，那是怎么回事......这就是替代政策
So the question is how does it when there's multiple lines in a set how does it determine which to over overwrite
所以问题是如何在一组中有多行时如何确定哪些过度覆盖
And that was the previous question probably maybe I should have repeated it
这就是之前的问题，也许我应该重复一遍
So you try to pick a line that was least recently used
因此，你尝试选择最近最少使用的行
So lines that haven't been accessed
所以没有访问过的行
Recently are good candidates for replacement because
最近很适合替换，因为
Because of the sort of inverse locality principle right that
由于这种反向局部性原理的正确性
They haven't been inverse referenced recently chances are they won't be referenced
它们最近没有被反向引用它们不会被引用的可能性很大
Again it
再一次
Oh yeah there's additional bits that I'm not showing here that you have to
哦，是的，还有一些我不会在这里展示你需要的东西
So when you replace a line in the set
所以当你替换集合中的一行时
If that data is has changed then it has to be written back to memory
如果该数据已更改，则必须将其写回内存
And that's another bit I haven't shown
这是我没有表现出来的另一点
Yes
是
[student speaking]
[学生说话]
Ah so yeah,so this is a really this is really tricky parameter writing
啊，所以是的，所以这真是一个非常棘手的参数写作
It's a high level system parameter that it goes on for years
它是一个高级系统参数，它持续多年
So the idea you want to have blocks in order to exploit spatial locality
所以你想要拥有块以利用空间局部性的想法
Right think about if you're going to go to the trouble of if you have a miss in cache
正确的想一想，如果你错过缓存，你是否会遇到麻烦
And you're going to go to the trouble of going all the way to memory to get some data
而且你将会遇到一路走向内存以获取一些数据的麻烦
You want to amortize the cost of fetching that data by fetching more than one byte
你希望通过获取多个字节来分摊获取该数据的成本
That's the motivation for blocks
这是块的动机
Because by the principle of locality in spatial locality in particular
因为特别是在空间局部性的原则上
If you reference a word inside of a block
如果你引用块内的单词
Chances are you're going to reference a nearby word which will also be an epilogue
你可能会引用附近的单词，这也是一个结尾
Okay so blocks the whole purpose of blocks is to exploit spatial locality
好吧阻止块的整个目的是利用空间局部性
Now if you make your block too small then you don't amortize
现在，如果你的块太小，那么你就不会摊销
You don't get the same amortization right you maybe get one
你没有获得相同的摊销权，你可能得到一个
You bring the block in
你把块带进来
So there's a reference you get a miss you bring the block in
所以有一个参考，你得到一个小姐，你带来了块
There's another reference nearby you get a hit because the blocks in memory
附近有另一个参考，因为内存中的块，你会受到打击
But then the next reference is in a different block
但接下来的参考文献是在不同的块中
Because your block sizes are too small
因为你的块大小太小
Right so you kind of want to make blocks big as big as possible
是的，所以你想要制作尽可能大的积木
But without slowing the system down
但不会减慢系统速度
So if you made your block size too big it would just take too long to bring that block in
因此，如果你将块大小设置得过大，则需要花费太长时间才能使用该块
Plus now your blocks,that your blocks are taking up bits in your cache memory
再加上你的块，你的块占用缓存内存中的位
So now there's no room for other blocks
所以现在没有其他街区的空间了
Right so it's a really tricky design problem right and
对，所以这是一个非常棘手的设计问题
If we're doing it taking an architecture class then we would sort of dive into the
如果我们正在做一个建筑类课程，那么我们就会深入研究
You know how how architects make those design decisions
你知道建筑师如何做出这些设计决策
But in general that's what it's kind of a balancing act right
但总的来说，这是一种平衡行为
Were there any other questions? yes
还有其他问题吗？是
[student speaking]
[学生说话]
Oh the question is every time there's a miss
哦问题是每次都有错过
Do you have to select a victim line and override it
你是否必须选择受害者行并覆盖它
Yeah I don't know of any caches that don't do that
是的我不知道任何不这样做的缓存
Now we'll see when we look at rights
现在我们将看到我们何时看待权利
We'll see there's an option of whether we're only looking at reads right now
我们会看到有一个选项，我们是否只是立即查看读取
But with rights that question does come up
但是权利确实会出现问题
If you wait in a couple of slides we'll go over that
如果你在几张幻灯片中等待，我们就会过去
Any other questions
还有其他问题吗
Okay so let's look at this two-way associative cache now
好的，现在让我们来看看这个双向关联缓存
There's one block offset bit
有一个块偏移位
We only have two sets so that we only need one set index
我们只有两个集合，所以我们只需要一个集合索引
And then the remaining two bits are tagged
然后标记剩下的两位
So let's go through our trace so address zero has a set is in set zero right here that's a miss
所以让我们通过我们的跟踪，所以地址零有一个集合在这里设置为零，这是一个未命中
so we load that into memory
所以我们把它加载到内存中
With the reference to address one
参考地址一
That's in set zero and that's a hit because that byte is in a block
这是设置为零，这是一个命中，因为该字节在一个块中
The reference to seven is a miss that's in set one so we load that
对七的引用是在第一组中的未命中，因此我们加载它
And we were just picking randomly pick one of these two over right
而我们只是随意挑选这两个中的一个
Because the cache is empty
因为缓存是空的
The next reference is to address number eight which is in set zero
下一个参考是地址为零的地址
Now here's the difference between the direct mapped cache and this 2-way set associative cache
现在，这是直接映射缓存和这个双向组关联缓存之间的区别
When we reference address 8
当我们引用地址8时
That block has to the corresponding block has to go into set 0
该块必须进入相应的块才能进入设置0
Because of this zero set index bit
因为这个零设置索引位
But we've got room now because we are set to have room for two lines instead of one
但是我们现在已经有了空间，因为我们可以设置两条线而不是一条线
So when we load that in well if we have an available empty slot
因此，如果我们有一个可用的空槽，那么当我们将其加载到井中时
We'll put it there we won't overwrite anything right so if possible always try to overwrite empty lines
我们将它放在那里我们不会覆盖任何正确的，所以如果可能的话总是试图覆盖空行
So now we've got in this set...we've got block 0-1 and block 8-9
所以现在我们已经进入了这个集合......我们有0-1区块和8-9区块
So when we get our reference to address zero
所以当我们得到我们的地址零参考时
Whereas before with the when we had a conflict miss in the direct map cache
而在之前我们在直接地图缓存中发生了冲突错过
Now we can satisfy that that request
现在我们可以满足那个要求
It hits in memory and the cache can satisfy it from the cache instead of going to memory
它在内存中命中，缓存可以从缓存中满足它而不是去内存
Okay so that makes sense
好的，这样才有意义
Okay now what about rights?
好的，现在权利怎么样？
So there's multiple copies of the data
所以有多个数据副本
Right we're sub setting as we move up the hierarchy we're creating subsets of the data in the caches
我们正在进行子设置，因为我们在层次结构中向上移动，我们在缓存中创建数据的子集
So what we do a write to a word within a block that's currently in the cache
那么我们对当前在缓存中的块内的单词进行写操作
Okay we have two options
好的，我们有两个选择
We can write that block immediately to memory right
我们可以立即将该块写入内存
We're got a block that's like this big and we're updating a little chunk of it
我们有一个像这样大的块，我们正在更新它的一小部分
So we can either do the update and then flush it to memory immediately
所以我们可以进行更新，然后立即将其刷新到内存中
So that memory always mirrors the contents of memory always mirror the contents of the cache
因此，内存始终镜像内存的内容始终镜像缓存的内容
Okay but that's expensive right
好吧，但这是昂贵的权利
I mean you know memory accesses are expensive
我的意思是你知道内存访问很昂贵
The other so the other option is what what's called write back
另一个是另一个选择就是所谓的回写
So in this case when we write to a block in the cache
所以在这种情况下我们写入缓存中的块
We don't flush it to memory
我们不会将其刷新到内存中
Until we elect that particular line as a victim that's going to be overwritten
直到我们选择那条特定的线作为受害者才会被覆盖
And only then when we're just we sort of defer
只有这样，当我们只是推迟时
The writing to memory until the last possible minute
写入内存直到最后一分钟
We defer it until just before the cache would overwrite that  that data block
我们将其推迟到缓存覆盖该数据块之前
Okay so that's called right back
好的，这就叫回来吧
And for right back you need to have some an extra bit in the line that indicates whether that blocks been written to
对于右后卫，你需要在行中加一些额外的位来指示是否写入了这些块
So the algorithm is when the cache identifies a particular line to overwrite
因此，算法是在缓存标识要覆盖的特定行时
It checks the dirty bit on that line if it's set then it writes that data to back to disk
它检查该行上的脏位，如果已设置，则将该数据写回磁盘
Okay if the data hasn't...if that block hasn't been written there's no point there's no need to write it back
好的，如果数据没有...如果没有写入该块那么没有必要将其写回来
Because it has the same value as the copy of the block on disk
因为它与磁盘上块的副本具有相同的值
Okay now so what about...so that's a right here now what happens if we have a right miss
好的，那么......那么现在就在这里，如果我们有一个正确的错过会发生什么
So we're doing a write to memory
所以我们正在写一个内存
And the word that we're writing is not contained in any block that's in our cache
我们写的字不包含在缓存中的任何块中
So we have two options we can do what's called write allocate so we can treat it if there's a miss
所以我们有两个选项，我们可以做什么叫做写分配，所以我们可以处理它，如果有一个错过
We can do sort of the symmetric thing that we did with a hit which was create a new
我们可以做一些对称的事情，我们用一个创建新的命中
A newline possibly overwriting an existing line
换行符可能会覆盖现有行
And then write in so we could create that cache enter that cache line
然后写入，以便我们可以创建该缓存进入该缓存行
Fetch it from memory and then do the right
从内存中获取它，然后执行右键
Okay so this is sort of symmetric to reads right then
好的，所以这对于那时的读取来说是对称的
So every right if it misses when the write finishes the that block will be in the cache
因此，如果在写入完成该块时未命中，则每个权限都将在缓存中
And if we do a subsequent read we get a hit
如果我们进行后续阅读，我们会受到打击
Okay so that's the reason you might want to do that
好的，这就是你可能想要这样做的原因
The the other option is just to
另一种选择就是
Don't allocate an entry in the cache don't allocate a new line just write write the data directly to memory
不要在缓存中分配条目不要分配新行只是将数据直接写入内存
You don't really need to understand the distinction between these two things
你真的不需要理解这两件事之间的区别
Different caches use different policies
不同的缓存使用不同的策略
For your own mental model a good model to use is just to assume write back write allocate
对于你自己的心理模型，一个好的模型就是假设写回写分配
So just assume that we won't copy the data to disk
所以假设我们不会将数据复制到磁盘
If there's a hit we won't write it back to disk until the last possible minute
如果有击中，我们将不会在最后一刻之前将其写回磁盘
And every time there's a write miss what will create a new entry in the cache
每次有写错过什么都会在缓存中创建一个新条目
Okay so that's...that I think that's sort of the simplest model that
好的，那就是......我觉得那是最简单的模型
And it's a reason it's a reasonable model that you can use regardless of the particular cache implementation
这是一个合理的模型，无论特定的缓存实现如何，你都可以使用它
Now in a real system so far we've only looked at we've only assumed that there's a single cache
到目前为止，在一个真实的系统中，我们只看到我们只假设有一个缓存
But in a in real systems there's multiple caches
但在实际系统中，有多个缓存
So modern core i7 has well architecture from intel
所以现代核心i7拥有来自英特尔的良好架构
Contains multiple processor cores
包含多个处理器核心
So 4 is a typical number for like desktop systems
所以4是类似桌面系统的典型数字
8~12 is typical for server class systems
8~12是服务器类系统的典型代表
These processor cores can each execute their own independent instruction stream in parallel
这些处理器内核可以各自并行执行它们自己的独立指令流
And each processor core can contains general-purpose registers which that's level 0 in the cache
并且每个处理器内核可以包含通用寄存器，其在高速缓存中为0级
And then two different kinds of L1 caches
然后是两种不同的L1缓存
The data cache the L1 d-cache
数据缓存L1 d缓存
And the i-cache is the...which is the instruction cache
而i-cache是​​......这是指令缓存
And these are fairly small 32 k bytes they're eight-way associative
这些是相当小的32 k字节，它们是八路关联的
And they can be accessed in a very small number of cycles
并且可以在极少数周期内访问它们
The next level of the hierarchy is L2 cache
层次结构的下一级是L2缓存
Which is still fairly small 256 k bytes same associativity
这仍然是相当小的256 k字节相同的关联性
And it has a slightly longer access time
它的访问时间稍长
And it's unified in the sense that the L2 cache contains both data and instructions
在L2缓存包含数据和指令的意义上，它是统一的
Ok so that's all within a single core on the chip
好的，所以这一切都在芯片的单核心内
And then also on the chip but external to all the cores and shared by all the cores
然后在芯片上，但在所有内核外部并由所有内核共享
Is at L3 unified cache which is 8 megabytes and 16 way associative
处于L3统一缓存，即8兆字节和16路关联
With an access time that's like 40 to 75 cycles
访问时间大约为40到75个周期
So if there's a miss in L1,then the L1 sense or tries to sends a request to L2 to try to find the data in L2
因此，如果在L1中出现未命中，则L1感测或尝试向L2发送请求以尝试在L2中查找数据
Since L2 is a little bigger maybe maybe the data hasn't been flushed out of L2 yet
由于L2稍微大一点，也许数据还没有从L2中刷出
If L2 can't find it,it sends a request to L3 to see if they can find the data in L3
如果L2无法找到它，它会向L3发送请求，以查看它们是否可以在L3中找到数据
If L3 can't find it then it gives up and it goes off chip to memory
如果L3找不到它，那么它就会放弃，它会从芯片到内存中消失
Yes question
是的问题
Yes name memory is this that's it's the DRAM built of DRAM chips
是名称内存，这是由DRAM芯片构成的DRAM
It's separate,it's in a separate separate set of chips on the motherboard
它是独立的，它在主板上的一组独立芯片中
Connected by those that I/O bridge
由那些I / O桥连接
That we and the bus various buses then that we talked about last time
那我们和公共汽车的各种公共汽车然后我们上次谈到了
And for all different for all of these different caches that block size is 64 bytes
对于所有这些不同的缓存，所有不同的块大小为64字节
Now there's a number of different ways to I think about the performance of caches
现在有很多不同的方法来考虑缓存的性能
My most common way is using a metric called the miss rate
我最常见的方法是使用称为未命中率的指标
So what this is the fraction of references that miss
那么这是错过的参考文献的一部分
So we're very so I thought and it's 1- hit rate
所以我们非常认真，这是1的命中率
So typical for caches to work that miss rate has to be pretty low
对于工作缓存来说，典型的错过率必须非常低
And fortunately because of locality these miss rates are low
幸运的是，由于当地的情况，这些错失率很低
Another metric is the hit time
另一个指标是命中时间
So if we do have a hit in the cache how long does it actually take to...
因此，如果我们确实在缓存中有一个命中，它实际需要多长时间...
Sort of look up the you know do the lookup to determine that there was a hit and then return the value
查找你知道的查找排序，确定有一个命中，然后返回值
So for L1 and in an intel system this is 4 clock cycles,10 clock cycles for L2
因此对于L1和在intel系统中，这是4个时钟周期，L2为10个时钟周期
And then there's an additional cost if
然后还有额外的费用
So you always have to pay the hit time right the hit time is the best you can do
所以你总是要付出命中时间，你可以做到最好
But if you have a miss then it's you pay the hit time
但是，如果你有一个小姐，那么你需要支付命中时间
Because you have to do the search and eventually you're going to have to return the word back to the requester
因为你必须进行搜索，最终你必须将该单词返回给请求者
But you then you have this additional cost
但是你有这个额外的费用
Which you have to go which is going to the the memory ready to fetch the data
你必须去哪个内存准备好获取数据
Okay so that miss penalty,that's what called miss penalty
好吧，这样的小姐罚款，这就是所谓的小姐罚款
Is on the order of hundreds of cycles for main memory
对于主存储器来说是大约数百个周期的顺序
But at other levels of the hierarchy it can be huge
但在层次结构的其他层面，它可能是巨大的
So the miss penalty if you have a cache in main memory
因此，如果你在主内存中有缓存，则会导致未命中
That's caching blocks that are stored on disk, the miss penalty is enormous
这是存储在磁盘上的缓存块，未命中的惩罚是巨大的
So it's kind of interesting if you think about it
所以如果你想一想它会很有趣
The performance of these systems is very sensitive to the miss rate much more sensitive than you would think
这些系统的性能对未命中率非常敏感，比你想象的要灵敏得多
And in fact 99% hit rate is twice as good as a 97% hit rate
事实上，99％的命中率是97％命中率的两倍
Yes
是
[student speaking]
[学生说话]
Yeah they hit,so the question is does the hit time include the time to access the tag and yes
是的，他们打了，所以问题是命中时间是否包括访问标签的时间，是的
So the hit time is the time it takes to just to search
因此，命中时间是搜索所需的时间
To determine if that item is in the cache and then return it
确定该项是否在缓存中，然后将其返回
[student speaking]
[学生说话]
Yeah so the yeah so the the miss the miss penalty is the time it takes for the cash to fetch the data from memory
是的所以是的，所以错过点球的错过是现金从记忆中获取数据所需的时间
So that's all the latency you know going across the buses
这就是你所知道的所有延迟
The time it takes the memory to respond to the requests
内存响应请求所花费的时间
The time it takes the data to flow back over the buses back to the the cache
数据通过总线返回缓存所需的时间
So the time for a miss is going to be the hit time plus the miss penalty that clear
因此，未命中的时间将是命中时间加上明确的未命中罚分
So I mean imagine suppose there's a hit time of one cycle and a miss penalty of 100 cycles that those are reasonable numbers
所以我的意思是假设有一个周期的命中时间和100个周期的未命中罚分，那些是合理的数字
So the the average access time if you have 97% hits
所以如果你有97％的点击率，平均访问时间
It's the hit time plus the percentage of misses times the miss penalty
这是命中时间加上未命中罚分的百分比
So that's four cycles for the average access time
所以这是平均访问时间的四个周期
But if we just increase the hit rate by two percent
但如果我们只是将命中率提高2％
The average access time drops by 50% a factor of two
平均访问时间减少了50％，减少了两倍
All right so why is this stuff important why should you care about it
好吧，为什么这个东西很重要，为什么要关心它呢？
So cash is that as we've seen are these these they're automatic they're all built in hardware
所以现金就像我们所看到的那样，这些都是自动的，它们都是用硬件构建的
There's no part of the sort of the visible instruction set that
没有那种可见指令集的那部分
Lets you manipulate caches and your assembly machine code programs
允许你操作缓存和组装机器代码程序
So that it all happens behind the scenes automatically in hardware
所以这一切都在硬件中自动发生在幕后
But if you know how kit...if you know about the existence of caches
但是，如果你知道如何使用套件......如果你知道缓存的存在
And you have this general idea of how you can work how they work
而且你对如何运用它们的工作方式有了一个大概的了解
Then you can write code that's cache friendly
然后你可以编写缓存友好的代码
In the sense that your code will have a higher higher miss rate than code that that isn't cache friendly
从某种意义上说，你的代码具有比不缓存友好的代码更高的未命中率
So the idea is to...you want to focus on making the common case go fast
因此，我们的想法是......你希望专注于使常见案例快速进行
Don't spend your time on code  that sort of code that doesn't get execute very much
不要把时间花在那些代码不能很快执行的代码上
So look at the most commonly called functions
所以看看最常见的函数
And then within those functions look at the inner loops of those functions
然后在这些函数中查看这些函数的内部循环
Because it's the inner loops that are executing the most
因为它是执行最多的内循环
Right so you can as a first approximation you can just ignore sort of stuff
对，所以你可以作为第一个近似，你可以忽略一些东西
If you have nested loops you can ignore stuff that's going on in the outer loops
如果你有嵌套循环，你可以忽略外循环中发生的事情
And just focus on the code in the inner loop
然后只关注内循环中的代码
Now what you want to do is try to minimize the misses in the inner loop
现在你想要做的是尽量减少内循环中的失误
Okay so repeated references to a variable is variables are good
好吧，如此重复引用变量是变量是好的
Especially if those are local variables
特别是如果那些是局部变量
Right so remember if you declare a local variable and see
对，所以请记住，如果你声明一个局部变量，看看
The compiler can put that in a register
编译器可以将它放在寄存器中
Right if you're referencing global variables
如果你正在引用全局变量，那就正确
Maybe not,the compiler doesn't know what's going on
也许不是，编译器不知道发生了什么
So it can't put the reference to that variable to see in a register
因此它无法将该变量的引用放入寄存器中
Okay so repeated references to local variables stored on the stack are good
好吧，如此重复引用存储在堆栈中的局部变量是好的
Because those will get turned into register accesses
因为那些将变成寄存器访问
You'll never go to memory
你永远不会去记忆
Okay also stride one accesses two arrays are good
好的还有一个访问两个阵列是好的
And they're good because of the existence of these blocks
由于存在这些块，它们很好
Right so the only way you'd know that stride one references our good is if you knew that
对，所以你知道如果你知道的话，唯一的方法就是知道那个步骤引用了我们的好处
Caches have the 64-byte blocks
高速缓存具有64字节块
Okay so the and stride one reference will have half the miss rate as a stride to reference
好的，所以并且一步参考将有一半的未命中率作为参考的步幅
Because if you're doing stride one references the first reference to a word and a block will miss
因为如果你正在做步幅，则引用对单词的第一个引用，并且块将会错过
But then subsequent references will hit
但随后的参考文献将会出现
Right and you'll hit if you're doing a stride one reference you're going to hit every word in that block
是的，如果你正在做一个步幅，那么你将会击中你将要击中该区块中的每个单词
If your drive if you're doing stride two references you're only going to hit every other word
如果你的驱动器如果你正在做两个参考，你只会打到其他所有的单词
Right so you'll only get,you'll get sort of half the so you'll missed at twice the rate
对，所以你只会得到，你会得到一半，所以你会错过两倍的速度
So
所以
So basically the point I want to make to you is that our understanding of caches
所以基本上我想对你说的是我们对缓存的理解
Allow us to sort of quantify this qualitative notion of locality that we developed the last time
让我们来量化我们最后一次开发的这种定性的地方概念
Right the last time we looked at we said if it's doing stride one references that's good if
我们最后一次看到的时候，我们说如果它正在大步推进一个参考，那就好了
If we're doing if we're accessing the same variable over and over that's good
如果我们正在做的话，如果我们一遍又一遍地访问同一个变量那就好了
But if we understand caches now we can quantify it in terms of miss rate
但是，如果我们现在了解缓存，我们可以根据未命中率对其进行量化
All right so let's finish up the rest of the class
好吧，让我们完成课程的其余部分
We're going to look at the performance impact of caches on your code
我们将研究缓存对代码的性能影响
Okay and why you need to why you need to know about these things
好的，为什么你需要知道为什么你需要知道这些事情
And that the impact that they can have
而且他们可以产生的影响
So there's a very interesting function
所以有一个非常有趣的功能
This actually plotted on the cover of your text book
这实际上绘制在教科书的封面上
That we call the memory mountain
我们称之为记忆山
I learned about this from a graduate student here at Carnegie Mellon back in the 90s who developed this notion made Tom Stricker
我从90年代卡内基梅隆大学的一名研究生那里了解到这一点，他开发了这个概念，让汤姆史翠克
And what it's a the memory mountain plots a measure called read through put or read bandwidth
而它是一个记忆山，它描绘了一种称为通读或读取带宽的措施
Which is the number of bytes read from memory
哪个是从内存中读取的字节数
So if you have a loop and you're scanning over a vector
所以，如果你有一个循环而你正在扫描一个向量
So you have a vector of say double words
所以你有一个说双字的向量
And you're reading those elements from a vector one after the other
而且你正在逐个从矢量中读取这些元素
The read throughput is the number of megabytes per second that you can perform that task
读取吞吐量是你可以执行该任务的每秒兆字节数
At and the memory mountain plots read throughput
在和记忆山图上读取吞吐量
As a function of the temporal and spatial locality in that loop
作为该循环中的时间和空间局部性的函数
Okay so in a sense it's looking at a wide range of locality options or characteristics in a program
好的，从某种意义上说，它正在考虑程序中的各种地点选项或特征
And it's plotting the performance of that memory system on that across that range as a two-dimensional function
并且它正在将该存储系统的性能绘制在该范围内作为二维函数
So in some ways the memory mountain is a
所以在某些方面，记忆山是一个
Kind of a fingerprint right every system has its own unique memory mountain
每种系统都有自己独特的记忆山
That we can measure right by writing a simple program
我们可以通过编写一个简单的程序来衡量
And so the idea here is that to construct the memory mountain
所以这里的想法是构建记忆山
We write a program called test
我们编写了一个名为test的程序
Oh shoot
哦拍
For some reason it's not
出于某种原因，事实并非如此
Okay right
好的，没错
So when we build a memory mountain
所以当我们建立一座记忆山
We're given a vector that consists of a collection of double words
我们给出了一个由双字组合组成的向量
And then we write a loop that reads those words that read some number of words in this case
然后我们编写一个循环来读取在这种情况下读取一些单词的那些单词
Hmm
嗯
There we go
我们走了
So it reads it reads elems number of elements right
所以它读取它读取元素数量正确
So we've got each of these double word elements with a stride of stride
因此，我们已经获得了这些双字元素中的每一个都迈出了一大步
Okay so if we have a stride of one
好的，如果我们有一个步伐
I know that was kind of redundant huh
我知道那有点多余了
So if we have a stride of one
所以，如果我们有一个步伐
Then we'll have our loop wills was sort of looped through
然后我们将循环意志循环通过
And read these elements until we've read elems number of those elements
并阅读这些元素，直到我们阅读了这些元素的元数
Okay and then we'll do it again and then that warms up the cache
好的，然后我们会再次这样做，然后加热缓存
Then we do it again and do exactly the same thing
然后我们再做一次并做同样的事情
So if we're doing this with a stride of two then we would be reading
因此，如果我们以两个步幅这样做，那么我们将会阅读
We would read this word zero or elem 2 elem 4 and so on
我们会读到这个单词零或元素2元素4等等
Okay so well then what all we're doing we're just for wide range of strides
好吧那么我们所做的一切只是为了取得广泛的进步
And a wide range of sizes
和各种尺寸
We're scanning over this vector and just recording how long it takes to do that read
我们正在扫描这个向量，只记录读取所需的时间
And then convert we convert that into megabytes per second
然后转换我们将其转换为每秒兆字节
And in order to I just wanted to show you this is we don't need,we're not going to go into detail about this but
而且为了我想告诉你这是我们不需要的，我们不打算详细讨论这个问题
This is actually how I generated the the cover on the book and
这实际上就是我在书上制作封面的方式
In order to use to exploit the parallelism inside the intel processor
为了利用intel处理器内部的并行性
Like you learned about last week there's a lot of parallel functional units
就像你上周学到的那样，有许多并行的功能单元
In order to exploit those I did 4x4 loop unrolling
为了利用那些我做了4x4循环展开
So I'm actually doing sort of four scans in parallel
所以我实际上并行进行了四次扫描
But the general idea is just what I've showed you here
但总的想法就是我在这里向你展示的内容
And this this 4x4 loop unrolling is just an optimization
这个4x4循环展开只是一个优化
But I wanted to show it to you because it actually it's the exact same principles
但我想向你展示它，因为它实际上是完全相同的原则
You learned about last week professor Bryant talked about code optimization
你上周了解了布莱恩特教授谈到的代码优化问题
So what we do is,we call this test function with these various ranges of elems and stride
所以我们所做的是，我们称这个测试函数具有各种各样的元素和步幅
And then we measure the performance and we get this beautiful picture
然后我们衡量表现，我们得到了这幅美丽的画面
This beautiful function ,to me it's beautiful I don't know does it look beautiful to you
这个美丽的功能，对我来说它是美丽的我不知道它对你来说是否美丽
So on the z
所以在z
On the z axis is plotting read throughput in megabytes per second
在z轴上绘制读取吞吐量，以兆字节/秒为单位
Ranging from 2000 megabytes per second up to 16,000 megabytes per second
范围从每秒2000兆字节到每秒16,000兆字节
This this axis is measuring is stride
这个轴测量是大步
So going from stride 1 up to stride 12
所以从步幅1到步伐12
And this axis is...so as we as we increase stride we're decreasing the spatial locality
而这个轴是......所以当我们增加步幅时，我们正在减少空间局部性
Alright
好的
And this axis is the size axis so we're going from I think 16k up to 128 megabytes
这个轴是大小轴，所以我们认为从16k到128兆
So this is the number of elements we're going to read each pass through
所以这是我们每次传递时要阅读的元素数量
So as we as we increase the size
因此，正如我们增加尺寸一样
We're sort of decreasing the impact of temporal locality because word
我们有点减少时间局部性的影响因为单词
As we increase the size there's fewer and fewer caches in our hierarchy can hold all that data
随着我们增加大小，我们的层次结构中的缓存越来越少，可以容纳所有数据
And so this so we've got spatial locality decreasing in this direction
所以这样我们就可以在这个方向上减少空间局部性
And temporal locality decreasing in this direction
并且时间局部性在这个方向上减少
So as a programmer what you want to do you want to be up here
所以作为程序员你想做什么，你想要在这里
Right good spatial locality good temporal locality
正确的良好空间局部性良好的时间局部性
Because you can get like 14 gigabytes per second measure agreed throughput
因为你可以达到每秒14千兆字节的速度来衡量一致的吞吐量
You don't want to be down here
你不想在这里
Which is only about 100 megabytes per second where you're reading out of memory
在你读取内存时，每秒只有大约100兆字节
Right so the difference between reading all of your data from memory
这样就可以从内存中读取所有数据了
And reading it from some part of the the caches is huge it's enormous
从缓存的某些部分读取它是巨大的，它是巨大的
Ok so because you're 213 students you'll be up here
好的，因为你是213名学生，你会在这里
And all the students that didn't take 213 they'll be down here
并且所有没有拿到213的学生都会在这里
And I've actually had I've actually had people several people write back
事实上，我实际上有几个人写回来的人
To tell me about their experiences you know in internships and jobs after they left CMU
告诉我他们离开CMU后在实习和工作中所了解的经历
Where they were given some code that that was down here
他们在那里获得了一些代码
And they recognized the locality issues and they got it you know better up here or close at least better
他们认识到了地方问题，他们得到了你在这里知道的更好或至少更好地关闭
So this picture this so-called memory mountain has all kinds of interesting features
所以这张照片所谓的记忆山有各种有趣的特征
First of all there's these what I call ridges of temporal locality
首先，我称之为时间局部的脊
Where these ridges see these ridge lines if you think of this is like a mountain
如果你认为这就像一座山，这些山脊会看到这些山脊线
You see this ridge line and you see this ridge line
你看到这条山脊线，你看到这条山脊线
And here's another ridge line and then here's a here's another one
而这里是另一条山脊线，然后这里是另一条山脊线
These correspond to different levels in the hierarchy
这些对应于层次结构中的不同级别
So this this top ridge line is where you're reading directly out of L1
所以这条顶部山脊线就是你直接读出L1的地方
And it should be perfectly flat and
它应该是完全平坦的
It's so fast that we're getting like measurement jitter performance jitter right
这是如此之快，以至于我们正在获得正确的测量抖动性能抖动
But it's and this little drop off here is a measurement artifact it it should it shouldn't be there
但它和这里的一点点下降是一个测量工件它应该不应该存在
It should be flat and go all the way to the wall back here
它应该是平的，一直到这里的墙
And then here this ridge line is where we're accessing L2
然后在这里这条山脊线是我们访问L2的地方
This is where we're accessing L3
这是我们访问L3的地方
And here's what we're accessing mostly from memory
这就是我们主要通过记忆访问的内容
So you have these ridges of temporal locality
所以你有这些时间局部的山脊
And then you have these slopes of decreasing spatial locality
然后你有这些空间局部减少的斜率
So you see the slope here
所以你看到这里的斜坡
As work so as we're moving from the top of the slope down to the bottom
正如我们正在从斜坡顶部向下移动到底部
We're decreasing our spatial locality so we're getting less benefit for these blocks that we're bringing in
我们正在减少我们的空间位置，因此我们带来的这些块的利益会减少
So you can see the we're getting less benefit out of the cost
所以你可以看到我们从成本中获得的收益越来越少
That we went through of importing of fetching these blocks
我们经历了导入这些块的导入
And once the stride hits the block size
一旦步幅达到块大小
Now every reference is hitting a different block
现在每个引用都会遇到不同的块
And so and then it flattens out then you get you're getting noes benefit from spatial locality
然后它变得平坦，然后你得到你从空间局部获得noes
And similarly here is where this this slope is where we're reading from L3
同样，这里的斜率是我们从L3读取的地方
And it flattens out always they always flatten out at the block size which is a stride these are double words right
并且它变得平坦，总是它们总是在块尺寸上变平，这是一个跨步，这些是双字
So it's stride of eight is 64 bytes
所以8的步幅是64字节
So once you exceed a stride of eight then you're no longer
所以，一旦你超过8的步伐，你就不再了
You're missing every time in a different block
你每次都在不同的街区
There's this interesting this one puzzled me for a while
这个有趣的是这个让我困惑了一段时间
You might be wondering like how come like over here is we increase the size
你可能想知道我们在这里如何增加尺寸
We can sort of getting the...we're sort of as we increase the size
我们可以得到......我们就像增加尺寸一样
We're doing most of our references out of caches that are lower in the cache hierarchy
我们从缓存层次结构中较低的缓存中执行大多数引用
Okay but except when we're doing stride one references
好吧，但除非我们正在大步提到一个参考
You can see all the way up to right at the end
你可以看到最后一直到最后
Right before it exceeds the size of L3
就在它超过L3的大小之前
It's flat
它很平坦
And it's running at the L2 rate
并且它以L2速率运行
Alright so here's the L1 rate and then it drops off and then it's running at a constant L2 rate
好吧所以这里是L1率然后它下降然后它以恒定的L2速率运行
Until the data no longer fits in L3
直到数据不再适合L3
So I think what's going on here is that the the hardware
所以我认为这里发生的是硬件
The cache L2 cache hardware is recognizing or maybe it's an L1 but
高速缓存L2高速缓存硬件正在识别或者它可能是L1但是
Some logic in the cache system is recognizing the stride one reference pattern
缓存系统中的一些逻辑正在识别步幅一个参考模式
Right because it sees all the addresses
是的，因为它看到了所有的地址
It's recognizing that stride one pattern
它认识到跨越一种模式
And then it's aggressively prefetching from L3 into L2
然后它积极地从L3预取到L2
So that those so it's fetching ahead of time it's anticipating
所以那些提前取出的东西正在预料中
It's saying look I've gotten five stride one references in a row
它说我已经连续五次获得了一个参考文献
I'm going to go grab a whole bunch of blocks and load them all up
我要去抓一大堆积然后加载它们
Because by the principle of spatial locality those blocks
因为根据空间局部性原则那些块
Those blocks are going to be referenced in the near future
这些块将在不久的将来被引用
So this was really neat and this only happened within the last couple years
所以这真的很整洁，这只发生在过去的几年里
So the intel engineers are always hard at work
因此，英特尔工程师总是努力工作
And maybe by the time the time we do the next the next edition of the memory mountain
也许到我们下一期的记忆山的时候
Those systems will recognize stride 2 and you know other stride pattarns two
那些系统将识别步幅2，你知道其他步幅2
But from this data it appears that it's only recognizing stride one
但从这些数据来看，它似乎只是认识到了一步
Ok so you can real...you we can improve the spatial and temporal locality of our programs
好的，你可以真实......你我们可以改善我们程序的空间和时间局部性
In several different ways that one way to improve the spatial locality is to rearrange loops
以几种不同的方式，改善空间局部性的一种方法是重新排列循环
And I'll use matrix multiplication as an example
我将使用矩阵乘法作为例子
So here's a sort of a simple matrix multiplication in code
所以这是代码中的一种简单矩阵乘法
Where we're multiplying a times b and adding it
在哪里我们乘以次数b并加上它
We're taking what's in of the c[i][j]
我们正在考虑c [i] [j]中的内容
And then to that we're adding the sum the inner product of row i of a and the row j column j of b
然后我们将a的第i行和b的第j行j的内积相加
Okay and then so we're going through and for each i,j in this matrix c
好的，那么我们将通过这个矩阵c中的每个i，j
We're computing an inner product and then creating that sum
我们正在计算内部产品，然后创造这个总和
So we can actually turns out there's a lot of different ways to do matrix multiply
所以我们实际上可以证明有很多不同的方法来进行矩阵乘法运算
And this is we can permute these these loops
这是我们可以置换这些循环
In any of six different possible permutations
在六种不同的可能排列中的任何一种
So this is a permutation where it's i followed by j followed by k
所以这是一个排列，其中我跟着j后跟k
But five other possibilities are feasible
但其他五种可能性是可行的
And so we can actually analyze those those different permutations
所以我们实际上可以分析那些不同的排列
And predict which one will have the best performance
并预测哪一个会有最佳表现
Okay so what we'll do is we'll look at the inner loop
好的，我们要做的就是看看内循环
And we'll look at the access pattern of the inner loops
我们将看看内循环的访问模式
And it's in the access pattern on arrays c,a and b
它位于数组c，a和b的访问模式中
Okay so let's look at the i,j,k implementation that I just showed you
好的，让我们来看看我刚给你看的i，j，k实现
So as always we focus on the inner loop
因此，我们始终专注于内循环
And if you notice this inner loop is doing a row wise access of column a
如果你注意到这个内部循环正在对列a进行行方式访问
And a column wise access,I'm sorry, a row wise access of array a
并且列明智的访问，对不起，一行明智访问数组a
And column wise access of row b
并且列b明智地访问
So row wise of a,column wise of b,we don't really care about c
顺便说一下b的列，我们并不关心c
Because it's not in the inner loop okay so just ignore that
因为它不在内循环中，所以只需忽略它
So given our assumption that we can hold in this case we're assuming that
因此，假设我们可以在这种情况下坚持我们假设
We can hold for of these integer elements in a in one block
我们可以在一个块中保存这些整数元素
So the row wise access which has good spatial locality will miss one every four accesses
因此，具有良好空间局部性的行式访问将错过每四次访问一次
Okay the very first reference will miss and then the next three will hit
好的，第一个参考将错过，然后接下来的三个将被击中
And then the next reference after that will hit a new block
然后在那之后的下一个参考将达到一个新的块
Okay so one out of four references to a will miss
好的，所以四分之一的引用会遗漏
But because the access pattern for b is column wise every reference to b will miss
但由于b的访问模式是列式的，因此每次对b的引用都会丢失
Okay so the average number of misses per loop iteration is 1.25
好吧，每次循环迭代的平均未命中数是1.25
Okay the j,i,k version is exactly the same pattern
好吧，j，i，k版本是完全相同的模式
K,i,j is a little different here
K，i，j在这里有点不同
We're doing row wise access of b
我们正在对b进行逐行访问
And a row wise access of c, so that's good right
并且明智地访问c，这样才对
So now we've got stride one accesses on both b and c
所以现在我们在b和c上都进行了一次访问
And the reference to a is outside of the loop,so we don't care about it
对a的引用是在循环之外，所以我们不关心它
So so both b and c will miss one quarter of the time
所以b和c都会错过四分之一的时间
Okay so the total average number of misses per loop iteration will be 0.5
好吧，每次循环迭代的总平均未命中数将为0.5
That's pretty good and i,k,j has the same similar behavior
这是非常好的，我，k，j具有相同的相似行为
Now j,k,i is sort of the exact opposite
现在j，k，我恰恰相反
j,k,i does column wise access of a
j，k，我按列进行a
And column-wise access of c so right we know that's a stinker right
对于c的列式访问权限我们知道这是一个很难找到的东西
And we qualitative well you know it's bad and we can compute that it will miss a one time per loop iteration
而且我们定性很好，你知道它很糟糕，我们可以计算出它会错过每循环迭代一次
So that will be two total of two misses per iteration
这样每次迭代总共会有两次失误
And k,j,i has the same bad pattern
和k，j，我有相同的坏模式
Okay so if we look at all these permutations
好的，如果我们看看所有这些排列
You can see that i,j,k and j,i,k miss 1.25 have 1.25 misses
你可以看到i，j，k和j，i，k小姐1.25有1.25次未命中
k,i,j has 0.5 misses and j,k,i has 2 misses
k，i，j有0.5个未命中，j，k，我有2个未命中
So clearly it looks like k,i,j and its brethren are the best option
很明显，看起来k，i，j及其兄弟是最好的选择
The only difference is that k,i,j has this additional store
唯一的区别是k，i，j有这个额外的商店
So there might be a question that is that going to create is that going to slow things down
因此，可能存在一个问题，即创造的是减慢速度
Well it turns out in systems in any kind storage systems rights
在任何类型的存储系统权利系统中都证明了这一点
Are much easier to deal with them reads
处理它们更容易阅读
Can you think about why that might be true
你能想一想为什么会这样吗？
So writes you have a lot more flexibility than you do with reads
所以写道你比读取更灵活
I mean yes
我是说是的
That's exactly so you can you have options you can do you can write back defer you can defer writing
这就是你可以做的选择，你可以写回来推迟你可以推迟写作
Until the value that you're written is actually used
直到你实际使用的值
But when you read an item you're stuck
但是当你读到一件物品时，你就会陷入困境
You can't do anything until you get that data
在获得该数据之前，你无法做任何事情
So it turns out that rights don't really that this additional store doesn't really hurt us
所以事实证明，权利并不是真的这个额外的商店并没有真正伤害我们
And so when we measure these on a modern system
因此，当我们在现代系统上测量这些时
You can see that that the k,i,j which has the the fewest number of misses
你可以看到k，i，j具有最少的未命中数
Has you see we're getting like one miss what we're plotting here is cycles per inter loop iteration
你有没有看到我们正在想象我们在这里绘制的是每个循环迭代的周期
So each iteration is taking about one cycle which is really good
所以每次迭代都需要大约一个周期，这非常好
This i,j,k pattern which is kind of the intermediate 1.2 misses
这种i，j，k模式是中间体1.2的一种未命中
That's sort of in between and the j,k,i which has two misses per iteration is the worst
这种情况介于两者之间，每次迭代有两次未命中的j，k，i是最差的
Ok so what's interesting is we could actually just by doing a little bit of analysis
好的，有趣的是我们实际上可以通过做一些分析
Simple analysis we could actually predict what this graph would look like
简单分析我们实际上可以预测这个图形的样子
Okay in the last ten minutes of the class
好在课程的最后十分钟
We're going to look at how to improve temporal locality
我们将研究如何改善时间局部性
Now so what we did with... when we rearranged our loops
现在我们做了什么......当我们重新安排我们的循环时
With in the matrix multiplication what we were doing was in improving our spatial locality right
在矩阵乘法中，我们正在做的是改善我们的空间局部性
But we didn't really do anything to improve the temporal locality
但我们并没有真正做任何改善时间局部性的事情
To improve temporal locality you have to use a technique called blocking
要改善时间局部性，你必须使用称为分块的技术
And this is important to understand because you're going to need it in your cache lab for one thing
这一点很重要，因为你需要在缓存实验室中完成一件事
But it's also a very general technique
但它也是一种非常通用的技术
Anytime you need,any time you're having issues with temporal locality
任何时候你需要，任何时候你遇到时间局部问题
Okay so
可以，然后呢
We're not going to go into too much detail this code but what I did I rewrote the matrix multiply
我们不打算详细介绍这段代码，但是我做了什么我重写了矩阵乘法
So that it operates you know a two-dimensional matrix that you can really just think of it as a contiguous array of bytes
因此，它运行时你知道一个二维矩阵，你真的可以把它想象成一个连续的字节数组
So I just rewrote this code to operate on a contiguous array one-dimensional array
所以我只是重写了这段代码来操作一个连续的数组一维数组
And then I'm doing the indexing explicitly here
然后我在这里明确地做索引
So here at c[i*n+j] this is n matrix
所以这里在c [i * n + j]这是n矩阵
So what I'm doing is...I'm accessing the I'm computing where the I throw starts
所以我正在做的是......我正在访问我正在计算我开始的地方
And then I'm going to the j column of that row and then accessing that element
然后我将转到该行的j列，然后访问该元素
All right so let's...but it's the same idea as before
好吧，让我们......但它和以前一样
So let's look at the miss rate for this, this is just an original this is an original unblocked matrix multiplied
因此，让我们看一下这个未命中率，这只是一个原始的，这是一个原始的无分块矩阵相乘
So what we're doing is we're computing c[0][0]
所以我们正在做的是我们计算c [0] [0]
And we're doing that by taking an inner product of row 0 and column 0
我们通过采用第0行和第0列的内积来做到这一点
So if you look at the we're assuming that the cache blocks holds eight doubles
所以如果你看一下我们假设缓存块有8个双打
And that the matrix elements are doubles then we're going to miss one eight of the time
并且矩阵元素是双倍的，那么我们将错过八个时间
Okay so in the first iteration
好的，在第一次迭代中
We're going to miss the first iteration does n of these things
我们将错过这些事情的第一次迭代
And since we're missing n over eight of the time
因为我们在八分之一的时间里都缺席了
We're missing one block for every eight references
我们每八个引用丢失一个块
For each for the first iteration we're going to miss n over eight
对于第一次迭代的每一次，我们将错过n超过八
And since there's n for each element for each block I'm sorry
因为每个块的每个元素都有n，对不起
And then oh so this is the number of blocks and the number of misses and then we have n elements
哦，所以这是块数和未命中数，然后我们有n个元素
So that the total number of misses is 9n/8 misses for the first iteration
因此，第一次迭代的未命中总数为9n / 8次未命中
Okay the second iteration will have the same number of misses
好的，第二次迭代将有相同数量的未命中
Because of our assumptions about the the size of this array
因为我们对这个数组大小的假设
So this these rows are way too big to fit in the cache
所以这些行太大了，不适合缓存
So we never get any we don't get any temporal locality
所以我们永远不会得到任何我们没有得到任何时间局部性
Okay so the total number of misses is 9n/8 times the number of elements that we're updating which is n squared
好的，总失误次数是我们正在更新的元素数量的9n / 8倍，即n平方
Okay so our total misses is 9n/8*n^3
好的，所以我们的总失误是9n / 8 * n ^ 3
Now let's rewrite the code to use blocking and so
现在让我们重写代码以使用分块等等
You can look at this code later
你可以稍后查看此代码
But it's much simpler just to look at it pictorially
但是以图形方式看待它会简单得多
So what we're doing instead of updating one element at a time
所以我们正在做的不是一次更新一个元素
We're updating a sub block a b by b sub block
我们正在通过b子块更新子块a b
And we're doing that just totally analogously to when an original case where b=1
我们这样做完全类似于原始情况，其中b = 1
This b by b sub block and c is computed by taking an inner product of the sub blocks
这个b乘b子块和c是通过取子块的内积来计算的
Of a set of sub blocks in an a with a set of sub blocks in b
a中的一组子块中的一组子块中的b
And for each one of those we're doing a little mini matrix multiplication
对于每一个我们正在做一点迷你矩阵乘法
So we're taking this sub block times this sub block
所以我们将这个子块占用了这个子块
Plus the second sub block of a times the second sub block of of b
加上b的第二个子块的第二个子块
Plus the third sub block of a times the third sub block of b and so on
加上第三个子块，一次是b的第三个子块，依此类推
Okay so we're doing the same inner product  operation
好的，我们正在做同样的内部产品操作
But instead of scalars we're doing it with these little sub these little tiny matrices
但是我们用这些小小的矩阵来代替标量，而不是标量
Ok all right so let's look at,let's look at what happens to the miss rate when we do this
好的，所以让我们来看看，让我们来看看当我们这样做时未命中率会发生什么
So there's there's n over b blocks in any row or column
所以在任何行或列中都有n个b块
And since there's b squared items in each block b*b
并且因为每个块b * b中有b个平方项
There's B^2/8 misses for each block
每个区块都有B ^ 2/8未命中
Okay and so then and then since there's there's n over b blocks in each matrix and there's two matrices
好的等等然后因为每个矩阵中有超过b个块，并且有两个矩阵
There's 2n/B*B^2/8 misses for this first iteration
第一次迭代有2n / B * B ^ 2/8未命中
So that works out to be an nB/4 and
所以这可能是一个nB / 4和
And the second iteration has the same miss rate
并且第二次迭代具有相同的未命中率
So the total number of misses is the number of misses for each iteration
因此，未命中的总数是每次迭代的未命中数
Times the number of elements in C that we're updating
计算我们正在更新的C中元素的数量
Okay which is (n/B)^2
好的，是（n / B）^ 2
So that all works out too it's still in n^3*(1/4B)
这样一切都有效，它仍然在n ^ 3 *（1 / 4B）
So in our first case with no blocking although that the number of misses is asymptotically the same
所以在我们的第一个没有分块的情况下，虽然未命中的数量是渐近相同的
But there's this pretty, this big difference in the constant factor so for no blocking it's 9/8
但是有这个漂亮的，恒定因素的这个巨大差异，所以没有分块它是9/8
For blocking it's 1/4b we're now we can we can just sort of drive that down
对于分块来说它是1 / 4b我们现在我们可以把它驱逐下来
By by increasing the block size so this gives us some control
通过增加块大小，这给了我们一些控制
But we still we have...we can't make the block the blocks too big because we need to fit three blocks
但是我们仍然有......我们无法让块块太大，因为我们需要适合三个块
In cache at any one point in time
在任何一个时间点的缓存中
Ok so the reason this is a dramatic difference right
好吧，这是一个戏剧性的差异吧
And the reason for this is that by doing the blocking we're sort of exploiting
其原因在于，通过分块我们就是在利用
Once we load a block into memory we're sort of reusing its items over and over again
一旦我们将一个块加载到内存中，我们就会一遍又一遍地重复使用它
So we're exploiting more temporal locality
所以我们正在利用更多的时间局部性
And matrix multiplication has this into this implicit locality
矩阵乘法将这种情况纳入这个隐含的局部性
Because the computation is order n cubed but the size of the data is n squared
因为计算是n阶的，但是数据的大小是n的平方
Right so we must be reusing some data items
是的，所以我们必须重用一些数据项
Right the problem with our scalar approach is that we were when we were reusing them they weren't in the cache
我们的标量方法的问题是我们在重用它们时它们不在缓存中
Ok
好
All right so the point that I wanted to make with you is that
好的，所以我想与你合作的重点是
Cache memories although they're sort of built-in automatic hardware storage devices
高速缓存存储器虽然它们是一种内置的自动硬件存储设备
And you can't really control them
你无法控制它们
If you know about them you can take advantage of your knowledge
如果你了解它们，你可以利用你的知识
And exploit them and make your code run faster
并利用它们并使你的代码运行得更快
Okay and the way you do this is like I said focus on the inner loops
好吧，你这样做的方式就像我说的那样专注于内循环
Do is try to do try to do accesses that a stride one
是尝试尝试做一个跨步的访问
And try to maximize to to maximize spatial locality
并尝试最大化以最大化空间局部性
And try to maximize temporal locality by reusing local variables
并尝试通过重用局部变量来最大化时间局部性
Which can then be put into registers
然后可以将其放入寄存器中
Okay so that's it for today good luck with your attack lab if you haven't finished it and
好吧，如果你还没有完成它，那么今天你的攻击实验室会好运
Don't forget to get started on cache lab this weekend
不要忘记本周末开始使用缓存实验室